A Guide to the Oakwood Avenue Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.), Records, 1916-1923
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Oakwood Avenue Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.), Records, 1916-1923
Library of Virginia
40587
0.45 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Virginia Electric Power Company Records, 14 May 2003.
Historical Information
Oakwood Avenue Baptist Church (now Oakwood Memorial Baptist Church) was established in 1916. The church's first pastor was Henry Lewis Nicholas. Services were held at Nathaniel Bacon School until November 28, 1920 when the congregation gathered at its new church at Chimborazo Boulevard and P Street. The church's name was changed to Oakwood Memorial Baptist Church when a new church was built on Gay Avenue in Henrico County.
Scope and Content
Records, 1916-1923, of Oakwood Avenue Baptist Church in Richmond, Virginia, including reports, minutes, correspondence, membership, officer, and teacher lists, building records, and financial records.
The reports and minutes series includes primarily reports, such as annual reports, committee reports (auditing, finance, building, missionary treasurer, Ladies Aid Society, Baptist Young People's Union, Sunbeam Band), reports to the Dover Baptist Association, treasurer's reports, and pastor's reports. The minutes are sparse. The correspondence, 1916-1923, includes primarily letters of admission and dismission concerning members. The subject files include information on church finances, the construction of a new church building, and the Dover Baptist Association, lists of church members, officers, and teachers, and Sunday school handbooks.
This collection came to the library as part of the Virginia Electric Power Company records. Norman Flippin, the secretary for Oakwood Avenue Baptist Church, was an employee of VEPCO and kept these church records in his office.
Contents List
- Reports and Minutes, 1916-1922, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - 1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1921-1922, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pastor's Annual Report, 1917, 1921 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1916-1923 (Box 1, Folder 7-21)
  Arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent or subject of letter.
  - In-House Correspondence, 1917, 1919, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - B, 1916-1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - C, 1916-1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - D, 1916-1921 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - E-F, 1916-1921 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - G, 1916-1919 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - H-J, 1916-1921 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - K-L, 1916-1920 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - M, 1916-1922 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - N-O, 1916-1923 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - P, 1916-1923 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - R, 1916-1921 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - S, 1916-1922 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - T-V, 1916-1920 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - W, 1918-1920 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Subject Files (Box 1, Folder 22-29)
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Church Manual, Covenant, and Instructions (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dover Baptist Association, 1917, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Finances (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Membership Lists, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - New Building Fund, 1916-1921 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Officers and Teachers, 1920, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Southern Baptists Convention Sunday School Board Handbooks, 1919 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 29)